the 41K versus the 1.1K between Claude
and Codex. That's super significant.
>> I would think about it more as a
difference in philosophy.
>> Mhm.
>> Codeex does a lot with little.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. It has these seven basic tools
and the descriptions for the tools are
very short. Whereas if we now look at
the definition of a tool from Claude, we
can see it's a lot more detailed. But I
would be surprised if Codex can achieve
these kinds of results without any kind
of training for these tools in
particular. Right.
>> And we also know the codeex. We're
running it with GPT 5.1-codeex.
So this is outside of the 1.1K which is
the tool description. You're talking
about an actual something that's baked
into the training to allow it to use
this. And the descriptions are therefore
just almost decorative so that the agent
with its training knows which ones to
use. but the the the core piece. So, so
very interesting and and maybe and I
guess this you know there's there's
there's a lot of guessing here probably
but you know perhaps Claude has maybe
had less of that training for in the
tools because of the amount of verbosity
in the uh in the in the descriptions cuz
it's probably you're looking at around
twice as much verosity in the in the
description given you're around uh oh no
>> it's it's about 20 times because if you
look at the difference in tools yeah
you're looking at about 20 times more.
It's it's quite a lot interesting very
of course we can speculate here because
we can't see the training but it's very
very interesting data and differences
between them
>> we can speculate and there are other
things that we see right like in our own
evaluations
we've had better success and in at the
moment our our sense is that sonet 45
opus 45 do better than the the codeex
models in using other tools tools that
they haven't seen before right like
custom tools
>> and so while yes Of course, Codeex and
Claude and Gemini, all of them support
MCP. You can add tools on top of them.
You can just invoke the model in your
own code, right? Like just as we've seen
with nano agents and give it whatever
tools you want.
>> We've had at least better success making
Sonnet make use of arbitrary new tools
than we've had with Codex. Interesting.
>> Not saying Codex, GPT 5.1, Codex and GPT
5.1 in general. Not saying it cannot use
tools, but not as flexibly.
>> Mhm.
>> And then there's a trade-off. What What
do you prefer? Right? like these tokens
always being in the context, they're
expensive. They cost you something. Even
with with caching, right? They take some
of the the context window and and they
they cost us something, but they give
you this additional flexibility. You
don't need to retrain the model in order
to swap the tools.
>> There is reason to believe that the
model would be uh sort of like more
capable. And again, this is something
that we're also seeing in separate
benchmarks uh with new tools that it's
never seen because it's like more of a
generalist as opposed to has been
trained on those tools in particular.
>> Yep. Interesting. So you mentioned
before there's a difference in planning.
Um what does that I guess what does that
look like? What what are the differences
in planning across models and agents?
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So, one thing that
that I um I lumped into planning is use
of cy sub agents like invoking a whole
separate agent.
>> We could talk about that. I wasn't sure
if it was the right thing to lump it
into planning because it's it's a whole
very very rich space.
>> But when we say planning normally,
right, ignoring sub agents for a second,
we mean exactly this. the model is
instructed, hey, uh if it's a complex
task, don't just try to to do it
willy-nilly and and do whatever you
want.
>> First of all, write to yourself and
there's there's a lot of research
supporting that models do better when
they first kind of like reason through
the problem and and create a plan
>> and just say what what is the plan or
write they don't say they they write the
plan and tokens out like to be added to
their context and now they'll be
following the plan.
>> Yeah. So both uh Codeex and Gemini have
a tool called update plan or something
along these lines and what they do what
they do in that tool is just the the the
model is invoking the tool saying here
are the steps I'd like to go through.
These steps are then added to the
conversation history
>> and that's it. There's nothing else that
reminds the model to follow the plan.
There's nothing that would would tell
the model, oh you you've skipped a step
or whatever. anytime the model wants it
can just emit a new update plan and the
user will be seeing whatever is the
latest plan that the model has has
shown.
Um, usually the model doesn't change to
to change the plan willy-nilly. And so
if it had steps 1 2 3 4, it does an
update plan. Now I'm doing one update
plan, same 1 2 3 4, but one is crossed
out. Update plan two is crossed out and
so on. And we get a sense of
progression, but actually the model can
do whatever it wants.
>> There's nothing in the uh aetic harness
that is running be around the model that
would remind it of things.
>> Claude takes a different approach here.
Claude has several uh planning tools and
update plan task complete these kind of
things like more nuanced and the agentic
harness actually kind of like supports
the model by reminding it oh you're done
with step two let me remind you that
before you said that you should be doing
step three now and so actually the plan
is nothing it's just tokens that the
model is saying in codeex and Gemini it
gets added to the message history and
now now the model is more likely to
follow that because it sees that in the
the the context that's gone by.
>> Whereas the plan is an actual sort of
like um uh element of flow control or
element of of control in in claude.
There is something that is not the model
that the agentic harness is actually
reminding it. Hey, are you sticking to
the plan? Are you following the plan?
Did you finish the plan?
>> Yeah. So that's again pretty substantial
difference I think on something that you
can see how often agents are planning
right like planning is a very um
important aspect of of agentic behavior
and yet such a difference in philosophy
>> but again all of these are very capable
agents all of them end up like doing
their plans pretty well even though the
the underlying implementation is quite
different. Yeah, it almost feels like,
you know, there's no right way or wrong
way by the sound of it because different
models are picking different things and
like you say, it's such a crucial thing.
If there was one way that was kind of
like showing, you know, much better
value, you'd think all models would
navigate to that immediately, right? So,
it's probably just more the way that it
was it was a choice of implementation
versus any major difference. But yeah,
super interesting to see such big, you
know, high-profile models just choosing
completely different ways of doing these
things and then sticking to it as well
>> and then sticking to it. We'll see like
uh I I don't remember if it was Codex or
Gemini. One of them already is beginning
to have cuz the the the repo is is open
source. It was already beginning to have
changes to some of its tools to be like
more geared more towards kind like the
the rich set. So maybe they are changing
tact
they're making a change over time.
>> Uh but yes the the seeing claude and
codeex that the distinction is is so big
between them clearly they thought about
it like this is not the first version
like we've been out there for some time
and there's a marked difference in
philosophy. This isn't their first LM
rodeo, is it?
>> Yes, this is their first LM. Exactly.